A Guide to the Walther and Hertha Riese papers, 1898-1975
Virginia Commonwealth University
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Walther and Hertha Riese papers, 1898-1975
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
1982.03.25
15.29 linear feet.
Riese, Walther, 1890-1976
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research, except for series 3, the majority of which is restricted under HIPAA. Please consult Special Collections and Archives staff for details.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Roland Villars in 1982.
Biographical Note
Walther Riese was born June 30, 1890 in Berlin, Germany to an affluent Jewish family. He studied medicine in Berlin, Strasbourg, and received his degree in 1915 from the University of Koenigsberg as part of an expedited program during World War I. After the war, he served as head of the Neuroanatomical Institute at the Frankfurt Clinic, where he shaped his ideas on holistic neurological function and treatment. During his tenure at the Frankfurt Clinic, he began a lifelong collaboration with neurologist and psychiatrist Kurt Goldstein. After the end of the first World War, soldiers often returned home with illnesses caused by the war. Many German psychiatrists diagnosed these veterans with conditions that could be noted as unrelated to the traumas of war, thus relieving the German National Insurance system of fiscal responsibility for their care. Riese, however, continued to work in his patients' best interests, diagnosing them with war-related ailments and recommending treatments that treated their needs comprehensively.
Walther Riese married fellow physician Hertha Pataky in 1915. Hertha Pataky Riese was born in 1892 to a Jewish-Hungarian family. She studied in Frankfurt am Main and Berlin, obtaining her degree in 1916. After the war, she was Director of the Frankfurt Social and Sexual Counseling Center of the Federal Government for Maternal Protection, advocating for birth control and providing abortion services. Like many who were sexual health proponents in the 1920s, she promoted sterilization as a form of birth control, a view which she later abandoned. The Center provided services to both married and unwed mothers, which was unusual during this time period as most sexual health centers catered only to married women.
In January 1933, with the rise to power of the National Socialist (Nazi) Party, the Rieses found themselves imprisoned for their religious, political, and medical beliefs. Upon their release, the Rieses and their two daughters fled to Switzerland, only a few days before the German government instituted their Jewish passport system. The family then moved to France with the help of a Rockefeller Foundation research scholarship, where Walther reestablished a research program on comparative neuroanatomy at the University of Lyon. When Nazis invaded France, the family fled to Canada via Morocco, before eventually entering the United States. With a letter of reference from Goldstein and a signed affidavit from birth control advocate Margaret Sanger, Walther, who had obtained another Rockefeller Foundation scholarship, and his family secured residency status in the United States.
Once in the United States, Walther obtained a position at the Medical College of Virginia (MCV), where he built a neuropathology lab and served as a professor of neurology and the history of medicine. Much of his research focused on the history of disease and neurology. He became a pioneer in the field of neuroethics, neurohistory, and traumatology. During his tenure at MCV, he published The Conception of Disease and A History of Neurology in the 1950s, where he described "neuroethics," a new concept in medicine. In 1969, in recognition of his life's work, Riese received the honorary title of professor emeritus at Frankfurt University where he had done much of his work between the world wars. Walther Riese died in 1976 in Richmond, Virginia.
Walther's widow Hertha lived until 1981. Her career in the United States took a different path. Despite her medical qualifications, she was unable to find a suitable professional position as a physician. In 1943 she co-founded the Educational Therapy and Day Care Center in a back room of the "colored library" in Richmond. The center focused on "extremely deprived" and neglected youth, particularly African-American children. The center later changed it's name to the Educational Therapy Center and, in 1948, officially became affiliated with the State Department of Mental Hygiene. Her work as director of the center culminated in the book Heal the Hurt Child published in 1962. She retired a year later.
Scope and Contents
The materials mostly focus on Walther Riese's professional work and life after imigrating to the United States. There are also materials related to his personal life, predominantly in Series 2 and 5. Some materials of and by Hertha Pataky Riese are included, primarily in Series 4. The majority of the collection materials are in English, with some in German and French. The papers are arranged into seven series.
Series 1: Research and Writings (1939-1978, undated). Series 1 contains of the writings of Walther Riese related to his many research interests. Of particular note are his writings and research files on aphasia and neurological disorders, as well as histories of numerous medical procedures and conditions. Researchers should also consult Series 5 for more information on his research interests.
Series 2: Correspondence (1915-1975, undated. Bulk 1940-1975). Series 2 contains the correspondence of Water Riese. It covers the majority of his adult life, and includes both professional and personal correspondence. While there is some early correspondence, the majority is related to his life after moving to the United States.
Series 3: Eastern State Hospital Files (1940-1960, undated). Series 3 is comprised of case studies from Eastern State Hospital case study files. It also contains correspondence, lecture and research notes, as well as an annual report.
Series 4: Educational Therapy Center Files (1949-1968). Series 4 contains case studies from the Educational Therapy Center while it was part of the Department of Mental Hygiene, and is the bulk of the materials from Hertha Pataky Riese.
Series 5: Subject files (1912-1975). Series 5 is comprised of both research and personal files. Many of the materials relating to Walther Riese's work as a professor at MCV, historian of medicine, and with professional organizations are located in this series. Similar materials may also be found in Series 1.
Series 6: Research Grants (1954-1967). Series 6 contains grant applications and other documents related to grants received by Riese.information on grants received and applied for.
Series 7: Publications. Series 7 is comprised of materials published by the Rieses.
Arrangement
Materials are generally arranged alphabetically and then chronologically within. Exceptions are: Series 2, Correspondence, is arranged primarily chronologically, with some correspondence arranged in separate folders by subject. Series 3, Eastern State Hospital Files, are arranged with case studies arranged alphabetically first, followed by other subjects alphabetically. Series 6,Research Grants, are arranged chronologically. Series 7, Publications, are catalogued in the VCU Libraries online catalog. Please see the Separated Materials note for more information on Series 7 materials.
Separated Material
Materials under Series 7 has been added to the General Collection, and can be searched using the library catalog.
Riese, Walther, 1890-1976; Riese, Hertha
- Series 1: Writings
  - Allegemeine Bedeutung Der Diaschisis, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aphasia, Semantic, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aphasia in Brain Tumors, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aphasia in Childhood Reconsidered, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aphasia: Auto-Observation of, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aphasia: Brain Disorder, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aphasiologists: Biographies of Ball State Univ., 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baudelaire as a Victim of Aphasia, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bernard, Claude, 1942, 1943, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Brain Lesions, Proofs, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Brain of Chimpanzee at Time of Birth, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Brain of Ludwid Edinger, circa 1960 (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - Brain Tumors, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brain Tumors in Children, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Brain Tumors in State Hospitals, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brain Tumor: Unusual Disseminated Brain Tumor in..., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brain Weight of the Babboon, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Brains of Prominent People, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brains: Burrow, Trigant, correspondence, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brains: Burrow, Trigant, Brain Study and Phyloanalysis, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Brown, John, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Brown- Sequard, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cancer: Clinically Unsuspected Carcinoma of the Lung With..., 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Casual Thought in Psychological Medicine, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Central Nervous System Brain Injuries, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Central Nervous System: Regional Physiology of the CNS, 1949-1950, 1952, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Cerebral Aging as a Result of Mental Activity, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cerebral Cortex of a Man Believed to be 107, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cerebral Cortex of Two Prominent Scientists at Old Age, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cerebral Dominance, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cerebral Localization, Doctrine of, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - Cerebral Localization, draft, 1940-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Cerebral Localization, correspondence, 1946-1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Cerebral Localization, Changing Concepts of, Lecture, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Charcot, Jean Martin, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Charlotte Lecture, Raw Material For, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chiarugi's, Vincent C., reform, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chorioid Plexus and Brain Development, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Classification, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Color Vision Specific Energy-Eye, circa 1959 (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - Condillac Analytic Method Relation to Pinel, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Condillac on Observation and Classification, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Connaissance et Moralite, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Consciousness, Duality of, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Cullen, William: Institution of Physic., 1955 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Cureau de la Chambre, Translations, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Cytoarchitecture in Huntington's Chores, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Descartes, 1957, 1963, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Descartes and the History of Moral Treatment, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Descartes as Psychotherapist, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Descartes' Animal Spirit, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Descartes' ideas on Brain Function, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Diaschisis, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Difficiencies: Research, notes and papers, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Disease and Art, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Disease of Van Gogh: Its Significance in the Life, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Disease-Conception of Disease draft, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  - Disease-Conception of Disease reviews and correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Disease: Moral Concept of Disease, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Epilepsy and Glioma, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Epilepsy, Post Traumatic, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Erster Entwurf Einer Pathographischen Methodenlehre, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Existential Psychotherapy, correspondence regarding, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Existentialistic Psychiatry, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Experimental Medicine to Experimental Novel, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Experimental Medicine: Passgage from Biography to Nosography, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Experimental Medicine: Preconceived Ideas in, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Experimental Methods, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Experimental Methods: Impact of Romanticism on, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Experimental Philosophy and Experimental Method, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Experimental Thought, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Freudian Concepts of Brain and Brain Disease, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Freud's Concept of Aphasia, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Galen, 1946-1974 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
  - Gall, Franz J., undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Goethe's Concept of Evolution, 1946-1949 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Goldstein, Kurt: The Man and His Work, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Goya paper, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Greek Medicine, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Hippocratic Approach, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - History and Principles of Classification of Nervous Diseases, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - History of Analysis, Basic Concepts of, 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - History of Anaesthesia-Discovery of Surgical Anaesthesia, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - History of Anatomy: Birth of Anatomy from the..., 1959 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - History of Aphasia, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - History of Diagnosis in Neurology, notes, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - History of Disease, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - History of Doctrine of Cerebral Localization, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - History of Etiology, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - History of Hysteria, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - History of Ideas in Neurology, 1945-1949 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - History of Ideas in Psychiatry, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - History of Insanity, Civilization and Insanity, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - History of Medical Ethics, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - History of Medicine, 1954, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - History of Neurology, drafts, notes, and correspondence, 1948-1958 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - History of Neurology, 1957-1961 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
  - History of Psychiatry, 1953, undated (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - History of the Terms and Conception of Neurosis, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Interpretation Rationale de la Vie, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Interpretation Rationale de l'Organism, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Ipsilateral Paralysis, 1946-1960 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Jacksonian Neurology, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
  - Jackson's View on Aphasia, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Kraeplin/Bleuler: Concepts of Insanity, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Lhermitte Obituary, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Life Without Forebrain, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - London National Hospital Lecture, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Lyman, Richard: Neuropathical Investigations, 1959-1961 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Maimondes, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Medicine: Should Medicine Split Into Different..., 1957 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Medicine: What is It?, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Medieval Attitude Toward Mental Ilness, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Medulla Blastoma- Report of a Case, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Mendel vs. Lysenko, undated (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Monograph, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Moral Thought According to Galen, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Moral Thought in Existentialism, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Mourgue, Raoul, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Muller, Johannes (see also oversized material), undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Nerve Impulse, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Neurology Devant le Positivisme, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Neuropathology of Mental Disorders, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Nodographic Philosophique, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Old Age, Changing Criteria, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Paracelsus, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Paralysis Angitans and Cerebral Aging, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Passions, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 6-11)
  - Pathology, HUmoral, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Pensee Causale en Medecin, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Penses Causale en Medecin, original text and English Translations, 1948-1954 (Box 12, Folder 1-8)
  - Perpetual Danger of Supernatural Diagnosis, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Petit Traite de L'Interrogataire, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Phantom Limbs, case studies, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Philosophical Pre-Suppositions of Present Day Medicine, undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Philosophy- Ideler, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Philosophy: Kant, 1963-1965 (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
  - Phyloanalysis, see also Brains- Trigant Burrow, 1960-1964 (Box 13, Folder 4-6)
  - Physician and the Patient, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Pick's Disease: Notes, Papers, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Pinel, Philippe, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
  - Pinel, Philippe, 1966, 1969, 1970, undated (Box 14, Folder 1-7)
  - Primitive Medicine, 1958, 1969, undated (Box 14, Folder 8-12)
  - Principles of Diaschisis, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Principles of Neurology, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 14-15)
  - Principles of Neurology, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Psychiatry: Impact of 19th Century Thought on Psychiatry, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
  - Psychodrama, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Renaissance, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Rosseau: Quotations from Rousseau for Classification, 1944 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Rush, Benjamin lecture, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Search for Man's Sanity, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Seneca, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Shock Therapy, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - A Short Treatise on Interviewing, undated (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Sommering, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Sources of Psychoanalysis, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Spinoza, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Stahl, G.E. (1660-1734), undated (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Straus, Aubrey- A Case of Parkinson's Disease, 1954-1955 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Structure Logique de la Contre-Epreune Experimetale, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Structure of Clinical History, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Structure of Indication: Therapy, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Structure/Function of Cerebral Cortex at Birth, 1944 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Structure/Function of Brain of New-born Bear, 1940s (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Symbolic Thought in Cartesianism, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Syndenham, Thomas, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Temple Medicine, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Therapeutic Interviewing of Aphasics, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Thought in Medicine, undated (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
  - Traitement Moreal et de L'Alientation Mental, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Vesalius, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Book Reviews, 1950-1955, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 1-5)
  - Requests for Reprints, 1955-1959 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Basic Books, Inc: Arthur Rosenthal, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Requests for Reprints, 1958 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Reprints by Others: Author Index, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Publishing Information, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Reprints Sent/ Mailing List, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Book Reviews by Riese, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Book Reviews, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Correpondence
  - 1915-17, 1915-1917 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - 1937-1950 (Box 19, Folder 2-15)
  - 1950-1953, 1950-08-1953-06 (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
  - 1953-1956, 1953-07-1956 (Box 21, Folder 1-7)
  - 1957-1961 (Box 22, Folder 1-10)
  - 1962- 1967 (Box 23, Folder 1-10)
  - 1968-1975 (Box 24, Folder 1-7)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - No Date, undated (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Family Correspondence, 1950s (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Publishing, Misc. Correspondence, undated (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Ilza Veith Correspondence, 1960s (Box 24, Folder 12)
- Series 3: Eastern State Hospital Files
  - ESH Case Study: Alzheimer's, 1941, 1953, 1955-1957 (Box 25, Folder 1-6)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Closed to Research Use
  - ESH Case Study: Aphasia, 1952-1953, 1959 (Box 25, Folder 7-9)
  - ESH Case Study: Arteriosclerotic Dementia, 1947 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - ESH Case Study: Brain Injury, 1944, 1949 (Box 25, Folder 11-12)
  - ESH Case Study: Brain Tumor, 1946, 1959-1961 (Box 25, Folder 13-16)
  - ESH Case Study: Chronic Brain Syndrome, 1955, 1956, 1958-1960 (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
  - ESH Case Study: Craniopharyngioma, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - ESH Case Study: Dementia Praecox, 1941 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - ESH Case Study: Epilepsy, 1950 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - ESH Case Study: Epilepsy due to Trauma, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - ESH Case Study: Involutional Psychotic Reaction, 1955 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Eastern State Hospital materials, 1949-1959 (Box 40, Folder 4-6)
  - ESH Case Study: Mental Difficiencies, 1942 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - ESH Case Study: Pick's Disease, 1958 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - ESH Case Study: Psychosis, 1944 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - ESH Case Study: Psychosis, 1952 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - ESH Case Study: Psychosis, Brain Tumor, 1945 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - ESH Case Study: Psychosis, Traumatic, 1942 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - ESH Case Study: Psychosis with Cerebral Arteriosclerosis, 1942, 1945, 1949, 1953, 1956 (Box 27, Folder 4-8)
  - ESH: Psychosis with Organic Brain Dis..., 1947 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - ESH Case Study: Schizophrenic Reaction, 1957 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - ESH: Notes on Senile Demntia, 1945 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - ESH Case Study: Notes on Senile Dementia, 1941, 1946 (Box 27, Folder 12-13)
  - ESH Case Study: Senile Psychosis, 1939-1942 (Box 27, Folder 14-17)
  - ESH Case Study: Senile Psychosis, 1943, 1947, 1949, 1954, 1957 (Box 28, Folder 1-5)
  - ESH Misc. Annual Report, 1958 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - ESH Correpondence, 1943-1960 (Box 28, Folder 7-9)
  - ESH Lectures and Research, 1949 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - ESH Lists and Titles of Galt Collection, undated (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - ESH Questionnaires, undated (Box 28, Folder 12)
- Series 4: Educational Therapy Center Files
  - ETC: Case Studies, 1949-1962 (Box 28, Folder 13-26)
  - ETC: Case Studies, 1961-1963, 1968 (Box 29, Folder 1-4)
- Series 5: Subject Files
  - Academy of Psychcoanalysis, 1955-1975 (Box 29, Folder 5-8)
  - Alcohol Intoxicated Dogs, 1942 (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - American Association for the HIstory of Medicine, undated (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - American Association of Emeriti, 1968 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - American Association of Neuropathologists, 1960-1974 (Box 30, Folder 1-4)
  - American Association of Neuropathologists Annual Meeting, 1951-1961 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - American Association of University Prof., 1968 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - American Federation of Jews from Central Europe, 19472 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - American Society of Mammologists, 1964-1971 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Aphasia: Articles, Reviews, 1960 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Aphasia, Class at RPI, 1964-1965 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Aphasia, Semantic: Clinical Notes, 1955-1959 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Aphasia in State Hospital Patients, 1954 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Aphasia: RPI Student Exams, 1961 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Archaeological Society of Virginia: Newletters, Bulletin, 1963-1970 (Box 31, Folder 6-8)
  - Aph. Society of Virginia, 1958-1964 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Archaeological Society of Virginia: Newletters, Bulletin, 1967-1970 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Baruch Center Physical Therapy, 1949 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Bieliauskus' Paper, undated (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Brain Hemorrhage- Research, 1949 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Brain Injury in the Aged, 1946 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Brain Injury Teaching Materials, circa 1951 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Brain Research, 1953 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Brain Tumors, 1950 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Brain Tumor's Natural History, 1945 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Brain Tumor: Glioblastoma Multiform, 1944 (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Brain Weight in the Aged, 1956-1960 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Brains of Bats, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Brains: CC Coleman, 1953 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Brains: Daniel Webster's Correspondence Regarding, 1957 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Brains: Old Brain Workshop, 1945 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Brains: Juvenile, undated (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Brains: Monkeys, undated (Box 33, Folder 6)